Guide to the Delmore Schwartz Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Correspondence, 1937-1966, undated; Series I; 1.42; (2 boxes)
  - Third Party Correspondence
    - To John Berryman from Isaac Rosenfeld of The Republic, 1943 July 9 (Box 2, Folder 142)
    - To Jennie Lee Davis from Mary Chase and Alice Hillon, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 143)
    - To Dr. Friedlander from Mark Van Doren and Sidney Hook, 1939 March 8 (Box 2, Folder 144)
      Regards Schwartz's teaching philosophy at University of North California Woman's College
    - To James Laughlin from Charles Pearce, 1942 February 9 (Box 2, Folder 145)
    - To Elizabeth Pollet from unidentified, undated (Box 2, Folder 146)
    - Unidentified, 1946, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 147)
- Writings, 1926-1966, undated; Series II; 11.5; (12 boxes)
  Writings is arranged into seven subseries: Poems, Stories and Essays, Reviews and Criticism, Drama, Lectures, Other Writings and Papers, and Writings of Others.
  Writings include holograph, typescript, composite, photocopied, and printed drafts of poems and prose with annotations and corrections. The series also includes empty white folders with notes by Schwartz's biographer James Atlas.
  Poems contains drafts of Schwartz's poetry, many of which include his corrections and notes. The bulk of the subseries is comprised of drafts of Summer Knowledge: New and Selected Poems 1938-1958, "The Studies of Narcissus," and untitled and unidentified poems. Stories and Essays includes extensive drafts of published and unpublished writings, including "A Colossal Fortune (for Marshall Allen and for Peggy)," "The Hartford Innocents," and "Kilroy's Carnival." Writings on T.S. Eliot represent an unfinished book by Schwartz. The subseries also includes introductions to other writers' books, dust jackets for his published works, and untitled and unidentified drafts and fragments.
  Reviews and Criticism includes writings on others' work, nearly all of which were published. The bulk of Other Writings and Papers consists of drafts that are difficult to read, fragments of writings, and untitled and unidentified. Writings of Others contains writings sent to Schwartz for his review and possibly to edit in his capacity as editor of Partisan Review, and Schwartz's personal copies of various writings. Included in the subseries is Schwartz's heavily annotated copy of James Joyce's Finnegans Wake and several of Elizabeth Pollet's poems, untitled writings and notes.
  Additional writings are located in Series III, Notebooks.
  - Poems
    The subseries is arranged alphabetically by title. Untitled and unidentified poems are grouped at the end of the subseries. Titles not contained in quotes are first lines of poems.
    - Abraham and Orpheus, undated (Box 3, Folder 148)
    - All clowns are masked and all personae, undated (Box 3, Folder 149)
    - "Apollo Musagate, Poetry and the Leader of the Poets", 1962, undated (Box 3, Folder 150-151)
    - "Aubade" from Mosaic November-December 1934 (Box 3, Folder 152)
    - "Birth, Copulation, Death", undated (Box 3, Folder 153)
    - "The Body's Sweet Secret and Secret Sweet", undated (Box 3, Folder 154)
    - "A Bohemian Comedy", undated (Box 3, Folder 155)
    - "Cantata, A. Lincoln", 1942 January (Box 3, Folder 156)
    - "Le Cimitiere Marin", 1961 June (Box 3, Folder 157)
    - "The Conclusion", undated (Box 3, Folder 158)
    - "Cupid and Psyche", undated (Box 3, Folder 159)
    - "Dr. Levy", undated (Box 3, Folder 160)
      Part of early draft for Genesis
    - "Dogs are Shakespearean, Children are Stranger", undated (Box 3, Folder 161)
    - "Dream of Whitman Paraphrased and Painted by Renoir", 1954 (Box 3, Folder 162)
    - "The Error", 1937 May (Box 3, Folder 163)
    - "Exercise", 1914-circa 1945 (Box 3, Folder 164)
    - "Exercise in Preparation for a Pindaric Ode to Carl Hubbell", 1959 (Box 3, Folder 165)
    - "The First Night of Fall and Falling Rain", undated (Box 3, Folder 166)
    - "Here is a Poem I Wrote Before I Died", circa 1965 (Box 3, Folder 167)
    - I am to my own heart merely a serf, undated (Box 3, Folder 168)
    - "Imitation of a Fugue", circa 1937 (Box 3, Folder 169)
    - "Interlude (Intervening Conversation)", undated (Box 3, Folder 170)
    - "Intervention", undated (Box 3, Folder 171)
    - "The Journey of Poetry Compared with the Variety of All Travel", 1961 (Box 3, Folder 172)
    - "Made in America", undated (Box 3, Folder 173)
    - "My Mind to Me a Kingdom Is", 1950 (Box 3, Folder 174)
    - "Phoenix Poem", 1957 (Box 3, Folder 175)
    - "The Poet", undated (Box 3, Folder 176)
    - "Poetry and the Poets", 1954 (Box 3, Folder 177)
    - "Present Moments", 1940 (Box 3, Folder 178)
      Includes several drafts of other poems
    - "Presto", undated (Box 3, Folder 179)
    - "Real Life (The Boys and the Girls)", undated (Box 3, Folder 180)
    - "The Sad Druggist", undated (Box 3, Folder 181)
    - "Seurat's Sunday Afternoon Along the Seine", undated (Box 3, Folder 182)
    - "Shenandoah or the Naming of the Child: A Play in Verse", undated (Box 3, Folder 183-184)
    - "A Snapshot of the Kingdom of Morning", undated (Box 3, Folder 185)
    - "The Studies of Narcissus", 1954-1959 (Box 3, Folder 186-189)
    - "Summer Knowledge", 1959, undated (Box 3, Folder 190-191)
    - Summer Knowledge: New and Selected Poems 1938-1958
      Listed alphabetically by section titles
      - Complete draft with typeset notes and corrections and book page numbers, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 192-194)
      - "The Deceptive Present", 1938-1958 (Box 3, Folder 195)
      - "Dream of Knowledge", 1938-1958 (Box 3, Folder 196)
      - "The Fulfillment", 1938-1958 (Box 3, Folder 197-198)
      - "Kingdom of Poetry", 1938-1958 (Box 3, Folder 199)
      - "Morning Bells", 1938-1958 (Box 3, Folder 200)
      - "The Phoenix Choir", 1938-1958 (Box 3, Folder 201-202)
      - Fragment, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 203)
      - Announcements, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 204)
    - "Swift", undated (Box 3, Folder 205)
    - "Vaudeville for a Princess", 1943 (Box 3, Folder 206-207)
      Includes Vaudeville for a Princess and Other Poems dust jacket
    - "Vivaldi", circa 1957 (Box 3, Folder 208)
    - We love while we see the sun, undated (Box 3, Folder 209)
    - "When God Was Famous", 1962 November (Box 3, Folder 210)
    - Will you perhaps consent to be, undated (Box 3, Folder 211)
    - "Words for a Trumpet Chorale Celebrating the Autumn", 1961, undated (Box 3, Folder 212)
    - A-Z, untitled and unidentified, circa 1938- 1966 (Box 3, Folder 213-226)
      General note
      These poems were grouped together by Schwartz
    - A-Z, untitled and unidentified, 1962-1966 (Box 3, Folder 227-231)
      These poems were written during his time at Syracuse University
    - Various poem drafts, unidentified, circa 1938-1966 (Box 4, Folder 232-248)
      Likely contain early drafts for Genesis
    - Table of contents for new book of poems, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 249)
    - Various poems from insert to The Library of Congress Twentieth Century Poetry in English recordings, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 250)
    - Poetry addenda for contributors' file, undated (Box 4, Folder 251)
  - Stories and Essays
    The subseries is arranged alphabetically by title. Untitled stories arranged by first lines and unidentified drafts and fragments are filed at the end of the series. Brackets signify a probable title taken from drafts.
    - "An American Dream", circa 1956 (Box 4, Folder 252-253)
    - "An American Fairy Tale", 1958 November-December (Box 4, Folder 254-255)
    - "The Animal", undated (Box 4, Folder 256)
    - "An Author's Brother-in-Law", undated (Box 4, Folder 257-258)
    - "Bank Night", 1935 (Box 4, Folder 259)
    - "The Birth of a Hero", undated (Box 4, Folder 260)
    - "The Birthday, The Metaphor", undated (Box 4, Folder 261)
    - "The Brothers Kennedy", 1955 (Box 4, Folder 262)
    - "Child's Universal History", 1943 (Box 4, Folder 263-267)
    - "The Children's Question", 1940s (Box 4, Folder 268)
    - "A Colossal Fortune (for Marshall Allan and for Peggy)", 1952 (Box 4, Folder 269-273)
    - "The Confession", undated (Box 5, Folder 274)
    - "Constance Forbes", undated (Box 5, Folder 275)
    - "A Day in the Thirties", 1950s (Box 5, Folder 276)
    - "A Dish of Ice Cream", 1950s (Box 5, Folder 277)
    - "Doctor Faust: A Dance Poem", undated (Box 5, Folder 278)
    - "Dostoevsky and the Bell Telephone Company", 1954 (Box 5, Folder 279-280)
      Part of "Memoirs of an Editor and Critic"?
    - "The Eden Party", 1940s (Box 5, Folder 281)
    - "An Evening of Ideas", 1940s (Box 5, Folder 282)
    - "Exercise", undated (Box 5, Folder 283)
    - "The Fabulous Twenty Dollar Bill", undated (Box 5, Folder 284-285)
    - "The Famous Elephant", 1940s (Box 5, Folder 286)
    - "The Farmer Takes His Time", undated (Box 5, Folder 287)
    - "The Feast", c1940s (Box 5, Folder 288)
    - "The Furnace", 1945 (Box 5, Folder 289)
    - "A Game of Tennis", 1939 (Box 5, Folder 290)
    - "Genesis", late 1930s (Box 5, Folder 291)
    - "The Gift", 1959 (Box 5, Folder 292)
    - "Hallmarks (or "RH")", 1940s (Box 5, Folder 293)
    - "The Hartford Innocents", 1958 (Box 5, Folder 294-298)
      Includes notebook
    - "Having Snow", 1950s (Box 5, Folder 299)
    - "The Headwaiter", 1940s (Box 5, Folder 300)
    - "The Heights of Joy", 1957 (Box 5, Folder 301-302)
      Include letter on back of page 22 to Mr. Basler
    - [Heinrich Heine], 1950s (Box 5, Folder 303-306)
    - "A History of the Boys and the Girls", late 1950s (Box 5, Folder 307-308)
    - "How to Read a Poem", undated (Box 5, Folder 309)
    - "How to Write Fiction", undated (Box 5, Folder 310)
    - In Dreams Begin Responsibilities New Directions publication announcements, 1938 (Box 5, Folder 311)
    - "In the Middle of Life", 1940s (Box 5, Folder 312)
    - "Kilroy's Carnival", undated (Box 5, Folder 313-319)
    - Two lyrics from Kilroy's Carnival, A Masque, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 320)
      Includes "Aria" and "Song"
    - "A Letter Day Romance", 1940s (Box 5, Folder 321)
    - "A Letter to a Former Sweetheart", 1937 (Box 5, Folder 322)
    - "The Locked Door", 1940s (Box 5, Folder 323)
    - "Love and Money", 1950s (Box 5, Folder 324)
    - "Love Stories", late 1950s (Box 5, Folder 325)
    - "The March Beginning (Modern Romance)", 1940s (Box 6, Folder 326)
    - "Maxwell's Crisis" fragment, undated (Box 6, Folder 327)
    - "Memoirs of a Metropolitan Child, Memoirs of a Giant Fan", undated (Box 6, Folder 328-329)
    - "A Metropolitan Gauntlet", 1940s (Box 6, Folder 330)
    - "A Modern Romance", 1956 (Box 6, Folder 331-333)
    - "Modern Romance and Freedom", circa 1949 (Box 6, Folder 334)
    - "The Moralist", 1940s (Box 6, Folder 335)
    - "Naming of a Hotel", undated (Box 6, Folder 336)
      Perhaps part of "Memoirs of an Editor and Critic"
    - "A Note on Arts as Imitation", 1936 March (Box 6, Folder 337)
    - "The Nun and the Ritz", 1955 (Box 6, Folder 338)
    - "The Pajamas Opera", late 1940s (Box 6, Folder 339)
    - "The Park", 1940s (Box 6, Folder 340)
    - "Publicity", undated (Box 6, Folder 341)
    - "The Rage of the Second Morning", 1950s (Box 6, Folder 342)
    - "Record", 1954 (Box 6, Folder 343)
    - "A Remarkable Summer", 1940s (Box 6, Folder 344)
    - [Richmond], late 1940s (Box 6, Folder 345)
    - "The Sense of the Past, The Past as Actual", undated (Box 6, Folder 346)
    - "Shyness", undated (Box 6, Folder 347)
    - Partisan Review announcement of prize for "The Statues", 1938 July (Box 6, Folder 348)
    - "Stick of Wood: Forty Years After", undated (Box 6, Folder 349)
    - "The Story of a Heart", 1937 (Box 6, Folder 350)
    - "Strictly Personal", undated (Box 6, Folder 351)
    - "Successful Love", circa 1960 (Box 6, Folder 352-353)
    - Successful Love and Other Stories dust jackets, 1961 (Box 6, Folder 354)
    - "Summer Colony", undated (Box 6, Folder 355-356)
    - "T.S. Eliot", undated (Box 6, Folder 357-360)
    - "Tales from the Vienna Woods", undated (Box 6, Folder 361)
    - "Track Meet", 1958-1959 (Box 6, Folder 362-364)
      Includes galleys
    - "Twelfth Night: Or What You Will", 1936 (Box 6, Folder 365)
    - "Twins in the Womb", undated (Box 6, Folder 366)
    - [Virgil Gibson], 1952 (Box 6, Folder 367)
    - "Washburn Story", 1945 (Box 6, Folder 368)
    - "The World is a Wedding", 1938 (Box 6, Folder 369)
    - The World is a Wedding dust jacket, 1948 (Box 6, Folder 370)
    - "Zola's Camera and Hegel's White Elephant: An Essay on the Philosophy of Fiction", undated (Box 6, Folder 371-372)
    - Fragment: "VI Metaphor", undated (Box 6, Folder 373)
    - Untitled introduction to Isaac Rosenfeld collection of book reviews and essays, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 374-375)
    - "To the Reader," introduction to untitled book of prose and poetry, undated (Box 6, Folder 376)
      Includes draft of writing fragment
    - Untitled introductions to anthologies, undated (Box 6, Folder 377-378)
    - Untitled
      Arranged by first line
      - "The girl woke up with a start.", undated (Box 6, Folder 379)
      - "Joan Marie Hadley Prunt slammed the door of her car shut.", undated (Box 6, Folder 380)
      - "My aged friend Cash Howells lives on the top of a small mountain not far away from my own home in West Jersey.", undated (Box 6, Folder 381)
    - Unidentified drafts and fragments, after 1930 (Box 6, Folder 382-386)
    - Unidentified drafts and fragments, after 1930 (Box 7, Folder 387-392)
    - Notes for planning stories, 1950s-1960 (Box 7, Folder 393)
  - Reviews and Criticism
    Titled writings are filed alphabetically at the beginning of the subseries. Untitled writings are arranged alphabetically by the subject author.
    - "Bell's Contribution", undated (Box 7, Folder 394)
    - "Novels and the News" from the The New Republic 1959 April 13 (Box 7, Folder 395)
    - "The Present Situation of the Writer in America", 1950 (Box 7, Folder 396)
    - "Religious Belief and the Readings of Poetry", 1951 (Box 7, Folder 397)
    - "The Saturday Show" from The Poconola 1926 August 7 (Box 7, Folder 398)
    - On Brownstone Eclogues by Conrad Aiken, 1942 (Box 7, Folder 399)
    - On Mimesis: The Representation of Reality in Western Literature by Erich Auerbach, 1949 (Box 7, Folder 400)
    - On Ulysses in Nighttown by Marjorie Barkenstein, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 401)
    - On Louise Bogan, undated (Box 7, Folder 402)
    - On T. S. Eliot, 1940s (Box 7, Folder 403)
    - On William Faulkner, 1940s (Box 7, Folder 404)
    - On Ernest Hemingway, 1940s (Box 7, Folder 405)
    - On The Poetry of Gerard Manley Hopkins, 1946 (Box 7, Folder 406)
    - On Further Speculations by T.E. Hulme, undated (Box 7, Folder 407)
    - On Stephen Hero by James Joyce, 1945 January (Box 7, Folder 408)
    - "Our Poor Dead King," on James Joyce, 1940s (Box 7, Folder 409)
    - On an article on Madison Avenue in the New York Times Magazine by James Kelly, undated (Box 7, Folder 410)
    - On Ring Lardner, undated (Box 7, Folder 411)
    - "Death of a Poet," on Boris Pasternak, undated (Box 7, Folder 412)
    - On Sunshine and Shadow by Mary Pickford, 1955 (Box 7, Folder 413)
    - On Thrones de los Cantares by Ezra Pound, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 414-415)
    - On Words for the Wind by Theodore Roethke, undated (Box 7, Folder 416)
    - On The American Establishment and Other Reports, Opinions and Speculations by Richard H. Rovere, 1956 (Box 7, Folder 417)
    - On Person, Place, and Thing by Karl Kay Shapiro, 1942 (Box 7, Folder 418)
    - On Allen Tate, undated (Box 7, Folder 419)
    - On Ivan Turgenev, undated (Box 7, Folder 420)
    - On Allen White, undated (Box 7, Folder 421)
    - On William Butler Yeats, undated (Box 7, Folder 422)
    - "Delights and Defects of Experiment" on New Directions 1944 from The Nation (Box 7, Folder 423)
    - On films and television, undated (Box 7, Folder 424)
    - Various drafts and fragments, 1940s (Box 7, Folder 425-428)
    - Clippings by Schwartz, 1951, undated (Box 7, Folder 428a)
    - New York Times Book Review instructions, 1962 May 14 (Box 7, Folder 429)
  - Drama
    - "Paris and Helen: An Entertainment", undated (Box 7, Folder 430)
    - "Venus in the Back Room", undated (Box 7, Folder 431)
    - Untitled, undated (Box 7, Folder 432)
    - Notes, 1940-1941 (Box 7, Folder 433)
  - Lectures
    - "Isolation of Modern Poetry" notes, undated (Box 7, Folder 434)
    - "Literary Dictatorship of T.S. Eliot", 1949, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 435)
      Includes announcement for lecture
    - "The Present State of Poetry/The Present State of American Poetry", 1957-1958 (Box 7, Folder 436-437)
      Includes 1958 January 21 Washington Evening Star clipping on lecture
    - Untitled lecture on current American poetry, circa 1956 (Box 7, Folder 438)
  - Other Writings and Papers
    - Notes and diary entries, 1946 (Box 8, Folder 439)
    - Notes and drafts of writings, circa 1942-1966 (Box 8, Folder 440-479)
    - Notes and drafts of writings, circa 1942-1966 (Box 9, Folder 480-516)
      Folders 503-508 likely contain early drafts for Genesis
    - Notes and drafts of writings, circa 1942-1966 (Box 10, Folder 517-544)
    - Notes and drafts of writings, circa 1942-1966 (Box 11, Folder 545-549)
    - English translation of Paul Valéry, circa 1930 (Box 11, Folder 550)
    - Bibliographies, undated (Box 11, Folder 551-552)
    - Contracts and Royalty Statements
      - Contract with New Directions for book on T.S. Eliot, 1944 (Box 11, Folder 553)
      - Royalty statements for New Directions, 1950, 1955 (Box 11, Folder 553a)
        Shenandoah, Vaudeville for a Princess, and The World is a Wedding
      - Contract with Doubleday and Company for "Collected Poems", 1958 May 23 (Box 11, Folder 553b)
      - Contract with Richard Bagley for all rights to Schwartz's dramatic works, 1959 November 17 (Box 11, Folder 554)
      - Contract with Corinth Books for "Short Stories", 1960 October 12 (Box 11, Folder 555)
    - Partisan Review rejection, undated (Box 11, Folder 556)
    - Various writings on Schwartz, clippings and photocopies, 1948-1951 (Box 11, Folder 557)
  - Writings of Others
    The series is arranged alphabetically by author. Leaves removed from books, dust jackets, and clippings and tear sheets are filed at the end.
    - Atherton, J.S. " Finnegans Wake: The Gist of the Pantomime", undated (Box 12, Folder 558)
      Includes Schwartz's notes
    - Bay, Victoria. Untitled poem, undated (Box 12, Folder 559)
    - Bazelon, David T. "To the Seventh Power", undated (Box 12, Folder 560)
    - Eaton, Charles Edward. "Della Robbia in August", undated (Box 12, Folder 561)
    - Eliot, T.S. "The Music of Poetry" and William Troy "The D.H. Lawrence Myth" from The Partisan Review Anthology, 1962 (Box 12, Folder 562)
    - Eliot, T.S. Bibliography, undated (Box 12, Folder 563)
    - English, Logan. "The Silver Star", 1965 November (Box 12, Folder 564)
    - Garfield, Richard. "Three Poems", 1965 (Box 12, Folder 565)
    - Gold, Herbert. " The Age of Happy Problems", 1962 (Box 12, Folder 566)
    - Grady, James. "Memorial Day 1953", undated (Box 12, Folder 567)
    - Hanlon, Robert. "Mardi Gras in Algiers", January 1958 (Box 12, Folder 568)
      Sent by Aldous Huxley to Hanlon
    - Heinrich Heine. Portions of Reisebilder, 1956 December (Box 12, Folder 569)
      Ordered by Viking Press from New York Public Library
    - Jacobs, Forrest. "A Sense of Direction", undated (Box 12, Folder 570)
      Handwritten draft of "Phoenix Lyric" on verso
    - Jespersen, Ruth. "A Sentimental Story", 1965 August (Box 12, Folder 571)
      Includes note to Schwartz
    - Johnson, Geoffrey. Various poems, undated (Box 12, Folder 572)
    - Joyce, James. Title page of Ulysses, undated (Box 12, Folder 573)
    - Joyce, James. Finnegans Wake, heavily annotated, 1939
      Conditions Governing Access
      Restricted fragile material. A digital reference surrogate is available in Beinecke Digital Collections. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
    - Malzberg, Barry. "In the Night of Memory: Two Scenes", 1964 September (Box 12, Folder 574)
    - Manning, Christian. "Horses in the Mountain" fragment, undated (Box 12, Folder 575)
    - Morgan, Edwin. "The Cape of Good Hope", undated (Box 12, Folder 576)
    - Mortimer, Ruth. "Dostoevski and the Dream," from Modern Philology, 1956 November (Box 12, Folder 577)
    - Ober, Doris. Various short stories, undated (Box 12, Folder 578)
    - Petria, Paul. "The Moving Reef", undated (Box 12, Folder 579)
    - Pollet, Elizabeth
      - Various poems, undated (Box 12, Folder 580-581)
      - "Arabella", undated (Box 12, Folder 582)
      - "Death is an Open Door", undated (Box 12, Folder 583)
      - "For Ruth", undated (Box 12, Folder 584)
      - "Puritanism and Robert Frost", undated (Box 12, Folder 585)
      - "Soliloquy", undated (Box 12, Folder 586)
      - Various notes and untitled drafts, undated (Box 12, Folder 587-588)
    - Rielly, Hernando. Various poems, undated (Box 12, Folder 589)
    - Shapiro, David. "January: A Book of Poems", undated (Box 12, Folder 590)
    - Singer, "Miss." Untitled poem, undated (Box 12, Folder 591)
    - Stanford, Don. The Traveler, 1955 (Box 12, Folder 592)
      Includes notes by Schwartz
    - Valéry, Paul. "A Course in Poetics: First Lesson" from The Southern Review, 1940 (Box 12, Folder 593)
    - Wood, Allyn. "Star of London", undated (Box 12, Folder 594)
    - "Philip." Various poems, undated (Box 12, Folder 595)
    - "O: A Journal of Poetry," volume one number nine, Summer 1964 (Box 12, Folder 596)
    - "Poetry and the Modern World symposium", undated (Box 12, Folder 597)
    - Leaves from books, undated (Box 12, Folder 598-601)
      Many are annotated by Schwartz
    - Dust jackets, undated (Box 12, Folder 602-603)
    - Clippings and tear sheets not concerning Schwartz, 1940-1966, undated (Box 13, Folder 604-610)
- Notebooks, 1939-1966; Series III; 7; (7 boxes)
  This series is comprised of notebooks containing Schwartz's writings, including poetry and prose, journal entries, and notes. Schwartz's handwriting is very difficult to read after 1960 and is often illegible. The notebooks' contents provide insight into Schwartz's erratic moods and alcoholic binges. After 1965, one notebook will often span three to five days. All notebooks were dated by Schwartz and titled notebooks are noted.
  Additional writings are located in Series II, Writings.
  - 1939-1953 (Box 14, Folder 611-651)
    Includes "The aid to memory"
  - 1954-1964 October (Box 15, Folder 652-682)
    Includes "Ulysses"
  - 1964 November-1965 June (Box 16, Folder 683-714)
    Includes "New Poems II," "History of Love/Notebook I," "From notebooks, poetry, notes," "Lyceum Gate II," "Joyce," "New Poems," and "Marriage in Love"
  - 1964 November-1965 February (Box 17, Folder 715-746)
  - 1965 February - 1965 June (Box 18, Folder 747-776)
  - 1965 September-1966 February (Box 19, Folder 777-804)
    Includes "Planner," "Metro: A Midwar Party," "Diana Cobb," "Diana Cobb VI," "Kilroy's Carnival," "Picture Shows II," "Diana Cobb Notebook VIII," "Commonplace," "New Fables, Parables, and Proverbs," and "The History of Love"
  - 1966 February-June and undated, 1966 February, undated (Box 20, Folder 805-814)
  - Notes filed among the notebooks, 1951-1965 (Box 20, Folder 815-817)
    Includes drawings
  - Collected clippings and printed material filed among the notebooks, 1951-1965 (Box 20, Folder 818-822)
- Personal and Professional Papers, 1936-1966, undated; Series IV; 2.25; (4 boxes)
  The series is arranged into four subseries: Divorce, Financial, Teaching, Other Papers, and Personal Effects.